Finding Aid for Walter F. Colby papers, 1924-1970
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Walter F. Colby papers 1924-1970
Colby, Walter F. (Walter Francis), b. 1880.
0.5 linear feet
8597 Aa 2
Professor of physics at the University of Michigan; personal and collected material.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Dr. and Mrs. Wilfrid B. Mann (donor no. 6444 )
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Walter F. Colby was a professor of physics at the University of Michigan. He was born in Rockford, Michigan in 1880, and attended high school in Muskegon. He earned his bachelor of arts degree at the University of Michigan in 1901 and the doctor of philosophy degree in 1909. He has also studied abroad, at the University of Vienna, Tuebingen, Munich, and Hamburg, and at the Behr Institute, in Copenhagen.
In 1906, Colby was appointed an assistant in the department of physics of the University of Michigan. He became full professor in 1919. During World War II, Colby participated in an army intelligence mission to Paris and Germany. In 1947 he was awarded the Medal of Freedom in recognition of this service.
In 1929 Professor Colby married Martha Guernsey, associate professor of psychology at the University of Michigan. He died in 1980.
This is a small collection of personal and collected material relating to the life and career of physics professor Walter F. Colby and his wife Martha Guernsey Colby. Included is correspondence, notes, reprints, and other materials relating to atomic research; also papers concerning research by David Dennison, Edwin C. Kemble, and Victor Guillemin; and photographs.
Subjects:
Colby, Walter F. (Walter Francis), b. 1880.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Physics.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; Physicists--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Physics.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Astronomical observatories.; Colby, Walter F. (Walter Francis), b. 1880.
Contributors:
Colby, Martha Guernsey, d. 1958.; Dennison, David Mathias, 1900-.; Guillemin, V., 1937-; Kemble, Edwin C. (Edwin Crawford), 1889-
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Personal and collected materials
  - Personal and biographical material (Box 1)
    (include collected German manuscripts, notably Heinrich Himmler letter)
  - Correspondence, research notes, and related material, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Martha Guernsey Colby personal and biographical material; also reprints of articles (Box 1)
  - Edwin C. Kemble materials (Box 1)
  - E. C. Kemble paper: "Molecular Models, Gyroscopic Motion, the Zeerman Effect, and Related Topics" (Chapter VII) (Box 1)
  - Guillemin-Sommerfeld paper on structure of methane, 1926 (Box 1)
  - David Dennison correspondence and research on methane, 1924-1925 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with Samuel Goudsmit, photocopies
    (originals at the American Institute of Physics)
    - 1926-1948 (Box 1)
    - 1949 (Box 1)
    - 1950-1951 (Box 1)
    - 1952-1953 (Box 1)
    - 1954-1971 (Box 1)
    - Undated (Box 1)
  - Manuscript account of Niels Bohr and wife, Margrethe (Box 1)
  - Photographs, (portraits, photos of other men (unidentified) and photos of observatory and equipment (unidentified)) (Box 1)